{"tossups": [{"question": "This leader\u2019s country was invaded by Charles Keightley\u2019s forces in Operation Musketeer. This leader\u2019s negotiation of a 1955 arms deal with Czechoslovakia enraged Anthony Eden, and his recognition of the People\u2019s Republic of China the following year caused John Foster Dulles to withdraw American financial support for the Aswan High Dam. For the point, name this Egyptian leader who, in 1956, nationalized the Suez Canal, sparking the Suez Crisis.", "answer": "Gamal Abdel<b> Nasser</b> Hussein", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "One member of this group was a saint nicknamed the \u201cLily\u201d of her people and baptized as Catherine. Joseph Brant was a leader of this group, whose members fought the Huron for control of the beaver fur trade in the late 1600s. This group was co-founded by Hiawatha, known for their longhouses, and fought on both sides in the Revolutionary War. The Tuscarora, Oneida, and Mohawk tribes are part of, for the point, what Native American confederacy, once known as the \u201cFive Nations,\u201d that is based in the American Northeast?", "answer": "<b> Iroquois</b> Confederation (accept equivalents for Confederation, like League or Alliance; accept <b>Five Nations</b> or<b> Six Nations</b> before \u201cFive Nations\u201d is mentioned; accept<b> Mohawk</b> tribe before\u201cTuscarora\u201d is mentioned)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A hero acquired one of these objects from an eight-headed beast whose heads were lured into eight gates baited with eight jars of wine. In 1876, commoners were forbidden from carrying these objects by the Haitorei Edict. A mirror, a jewel, and one of these objects named Kusanagi are the three sacred treasures of Japan. For the point, name these objects, such as the katana, that were used by samurai warriors in combat.", "answer": "<b> sword</b>s (accept<b> Kusanagi</b> before mentioned; accept<b> katana</b> before mentioned; prompt on grasscutter; prompt on generic terms like blade or weapon, but do not accept or prompt on knives or daggers)", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {"question": "This country\u2019s cruiser<em> Elli</em> was sunk by a submarine as a prelude to an invasion that this country defeated by capturing the Klisura Pass. Wilhelm List outflanked a defensive line in this country built by prime minister Ioannis Metaxas, who led this country when it was invaded by Italy. For the point, name this European country that the Nazis conquered in part by paradropping soldiers on its island of Crete.", "answer": "<b> Greece</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Part of this initiative involved the purchase of whaling ships for the sole purpose of sinking them in harbors, called the Stone Fleet. Vessels circumventing this initiative were controversially built in Great Britain and included Raphael Semmes\u2019 ship<em> Alabama</em>. This plan called for the blockade of vital ports like Mobile Bay and control of the Mississippi River. Winfield Scott proposed, for the point, what plan to\u201cconstrict\u201d the flow of supplies to the Confederacy?", "answer": "<b> Anaconda Plan</b> (prompt on descriptive answers like \u201cblockading the South\u201d) Page 1", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "The Committee of Public Safety was led by, for the point, what Frenchman who orchestrated the Reign of Terror?", "answer": "Maximilien<b> Robespierre</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "A politician with this surname was defeated by Bill Brock in 1970, fourteen years after he joined his home state\u2019s fellow Democratic senator, Estes Kefauver, in not signing the Southern Manifesto. A younger politician with this surname shared the 2007 Nobel Peace Prize after writing<em> Earth in the Balance</em> in 1992 and starring in a 2006 documentary,<em> An Inconvenient Truth</em>. For the point, give this surname of two Tennessee senators named Al, the younger of which was Bill Clinton\u2019s vice president.", "answer": "<b> Gore</b> (accept Al<b> Gore</b>, Sr.; accept Al<b> Gore</b>, Jr.)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In response to this event, Adel el-Mshiti wrote the song \u201cWe Will Stay Here.\u201d This event led to an election victory for the Ennhada Party, as well as fighting around the cities of Derna and Tobruk. This event, which began when a vegetable vendor named Mohammed Bouazizi set himself on fire in Tunisia, led to the overthrow of Hosni Mubarak and election of Mohammed Morsi in Egypt. For the point, name this wave of revolutions that overthrew Muammar Gaddafi and other north African dictators in 2011 and 2012.", "answer": "<b> Arab Spring</b> (prompt on Libyan Civil War; prompt on Tunisian Revolution)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Joseph Martin-Dauch was escorted out of a venue for this activity after voting against an otherwise unanimous agreement. Charles the Affable died after bumping his head on the lintel above the entrance to a venue where this activity took place. The father of King George III was either killed with a cricket ball or a ball used for this sport. In 1789, members of the National Assembly took an oath in a venue for this sport.<em> Jeu de paume</em> was a racquet-less precursor to, for the point, what sport played professionally by Roger Federer and Serena Williams?", "answer": "<b> tennis</b> (accept<b> jeu de paume</b> before mentioned) Page 2", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}, {"question": "One political party of this name adopted the slogan \u201cFight for Peace.\u201d Hiram Johnson ran for vice president with a party of this name, and three decades later, Henry Wallace revived this political party for his presidential run. One of these parties earned a nickname after a politician running on its party\u2019s ticket quipped that he was as \u201cfit as a bull moose.\u201d Robert La Follette\u2019s 1924 presidential bid and Teddy Roosevelt\u2019s final presidential bid were made under the banners of, for the point, what political ideology that sought reform in the early 20th century?", "answer": "<b> Progressive</b> Party (accept word forms; do not accept or prompt on Bull Moose)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A pathogen of this plant was crystallized by Wendell Stanley and studied by Rosalind Franklin and James Watson. Martinus Beijerinck discovered the first virus while studying mosaic patterns on the leaves of this plant. In 1912, oncologist Isaac Adler became the first physician to link this plant to one of its most infamous health results. This crop\u2019s long history of being grown in Virginia began with John Rolfe. For the point, name this crop that was popularized in England by Sir Walter Raleigh and that can be found in cigarettes.", "answer": "<b> tobacco</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "For the point, identify this winner of the Battle of Fallen Timbers who was nicknamed \u201cMad Anthony.\u201d", "answer": "\u201cMad\u201d Anthony<b> Wayne</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A prelude to this conflict was a rebellion led by Jack Cade, a \u201cCaptain of Kent.\u201d The Act of Accord attempted to resolve this conflict, which started as an attempt to remove the Duke of Somerset. The Captain of Calais, the Earl of Warwick, was known as the Kingmaker during this conflict, which ended after Richard III was killed at the Battle of Bosworth Field and led to the reign of Henry VII of the House of Tudor. For the point, name this series of wars between the Houses of York and Lancaster for the English throne.", "answer": "War(s) of the<b> Roses</b> Page 3", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "The main character of this story notices the stars arranged in strange constellations while walking through an isolated road in the middle of a dense forest. The protagonist of this story is struck by the slow sound of the ticking of his watch as he stands on the the title structure, which he had planned to burn down to stall the advance of Union forces into Alabama. For the point, name this short story about Peyton Farquhar, written by Ambrose Bierce.", "answer": "An<b> Occurrence at Owl Creek Bridge</b>", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Short Fiction"}, {"question": "A failed revolt against this emperor by Gaius Julius Vindex ended in a minor battle and Vindex\u2019s suicide. After the Pisonian Conspiracy failed to depose this man, he forced his old advisor Seneca to commit suicide. This man was accused of arson to clear land out for his Domus Aurea project, though he blamed that event on the Christians he persecuted. The Year of the Four Emperors followed the suicide of, for the point, what emperor who is alleged to have fiddled as Rome burned?", "answer": "<b> Nero</b> Claudius Caesar Augustus Germanicus (do not prompt on any of the succeeding names alone)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "This city\u2019s AT&T building is topped by two pointy towers, leading observers to dub it the \u201cBatman Building.\u201d This city, which served as the northern end of the Natchez Trace in the 19th century, celebrated its state\u2019s centennial by building a replica of the Parthenon. This city\u2019s musical legacy developed in venues like Ryman Auditorium and the Grand Ole Opry House. To ease tensions following the Civil War, shipping magnate Cornelius funded Vanderbilt University as a gift to, for the point, what capital city of Tennessee?", "answer": "<b> Nashville</b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "This politician lost power twice when Farooq Leghari and Ghulam Ishaq Khan dissolved Parliament using Eighth Amendment powers. This leader founded the Movement for the Restoration of Democracy after Muhammad Zia-ul-Haq deposed this leader\u2019s father, Zulfikar Ali, in a bloodless coup in 1977. At a political rally in Rawalpindi in 2007, a member of Al-Qaeda assassinated this leader of the PPP. For the point, name this first female Prime Minister of Pakistan.", "answer": "<b> B</b>enazir<b> Bhutto</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "As the holder of this position, Arthur Summerfield oversaw the test firing of a missile from the USS <em>Barbero</em>. In accordance with contemporary tradition, Franklin Roosevelt appointed his campaign manager James Farley to this position. Samuel Osgood was the first official holder of this position, though before independence, Benjamin Franklin held an analogous position because of his experience in the printing industry. For the point, name this position, formerly a Cabinet-level post, that is in charge of the U.S. mail service.", "answer": "<b> Postmaster General</b> (prompt on descriptions of \u201chead of the US Postal Service\u201d) Page 4", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This man was demoted, then reinstated after he claimed that Ulysses Grant\u2019s brother was involved in the Trader Post Scandal. This man defended the Union back lines while commanding the First Michigan Cavalry at the Battle of Gettysburg. Thirteen years later, this man ordered Marcus Reno and the 7th Cavalry to attack a band of Sioux and Cheyenne warriors on the \u201cGreasy Grass.\u201d For the point, name this military officer who was killed at the Battle of Little Bighorn, a battle known as his last stand.", "answer": "George Armstrong<b> Custer</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This event was prompted by unfavorable news brought by Mo Xiong [shee-ong]. During this event, the Zunyi Conference led to the removal of Otto Braun from command. A much-celebrated crossing of the Luding Bridge during this event was probably greatly exaggerated. The \u201cEncirclement Campaigns\u201dprompted this event, in which a military force was forced to flee from Jiangxi [jee-ang-shee] to Shaanxi [shan-shee]. For the point, name this year-long event in which Mao Zedong led the Communists on a retreat to northern China.", "answer": "<b> Long March</b> (or Hongjun<b> Chang Zheng</b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "A person with this profession called an American salvage operation of a Soviet sub \u201cProject Jennifer\u201dand wrote about Israel\u2019s nuclear program in<em> The Samson Option</em>. Seymour Hersh has this occupation, as did the creator of the television show<em> See it Now</em> who sparred with Joseph McCarthy. This is the occupation of Edward Murrow, as well as Bob Woodward and Carl Bernstein, who gave one of their anonymous sources the nickname Deep Throat. For the point, name this occupation of employees of<em> The</em> <em>Washington Post</em>.", "answer": "<b> journalist</b>s (accept synonyms such as<b> reporter</b>s or<b> correspondent</b>s; accept word forms; prompt on writers)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This territory last expanded in the War of Castro against the Farnese [far-nay-zay] family, and it gained its independence after the Battle of Legnano led to the Peace of Venice. This territory, which was created by the Donation of Pepin, expanded to include the region of Romagna [roh-man-yuh] thanks to the efforts of Cesare [chez-ah-ray] Borgia, the son of a ruler of this territory. This territory existed until 1870, when the unification of Italy was finished. For the point, name this pre-Vatican territory historically ruled by the Pope from Rome.", "answer": "<b> Papal States</b> (accept the<b> State of the Church</b> or<b> Stato della Chiesa</b>) Page 5", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This region provided the first documentation of turbidity tides after a 1929 earthquake struck the Laurentian Slope and caused a landslide. The \u201cflemish cap\u201d of this region lies just outside the Exclusive Economic Zone and is now a victim of overharvesting from international ships. A 1992 moratorium ended this region\u2019s once-booming cod industry. The mixing of the Gulf Stream and Labrador Current helped create, for the point, what shallow, nutrient-rich region southeast of Newfoundland in the North Atlantic?", "answer": "<b> Grand Banks</b> of Newfoundland (prompt on Newfoundland before mentioned, the (North) Atlantic Ocean, the Gulf Stream and/or the Labrador Current before they are mentioned)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "One leader of this name suppressed a rebellion by an alliance of Paraiba, Cear\u00b4a, and Pernambuco called the Confederation of the Equator. Another leader of this name passed the Eusebio de Queiros Law, abolishing the slave trade, and the Law of Free Birth, aimed at gradually ending slavery in his country; that leader defeated Argentina and Uruguay during the Paraguayan War. For the point, give the shared name of the only two emperors of Brazil.", "answer": "Dom<b> Pedro</b> (accept Dom<b> Pedro</b> I; accept Dom<b> Pedro</b> II after \u201cAnother\u201d is read; do not prompt on Dom)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This composer quoted the folk song \u201cOj, Magdolino\u201d in one of a set of sixty-nine pieces he named after a native dance form. The third movement of this man\u2019s<em> Piano Sonata no. 2</em> in B-flat minor was played at Brezhnev\u2019s, JFK\u2019s, and his own funeral. This composer, who fled his homeland shortly before the November Uprising, was a lover of George Sand, who gave his Opus 53 the nickname \u201cHeroic\u201d in response to the Revolutions of 1848. For the point, name this pianist whose mazurkas and polonaises paid tribute to his native Poland.", "answer": "Frederic<b> Chopin</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "A member of this group named George Mellor killed William Horsfall after Horsfall said he would ride \u201cup to his saddle\u201d in the blood of these people. A movement similar to this group centered on threshing machines and was called the Swing Riots. These people, who were targeted by the 1812 Frame Breaking Act, rioted in response to an economic downturn after the Napoleonic Wars and the growth of new textile factories. For the point, name these English workers who destroyed weaving machines to protest losing their jobs and whose name now broadly refers to people opposed to technological progress.", "answer": "<b> Luddite</b>s Page 6", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "An invasion of this country began with the storming of the Tajbeg Palace in Operation Storm-333, in which president Hafizullah Amin was killed. In 1988, Mohammad Najibullah helped negotiate a set of Geneva Accords that helped end a conflict in this country. An attack on this country prompted a Western boycott of the 1980 Olympics and a CIA effort to supply Stinger missiles to mujahideen fighters. The Brezhnev Doctrine was used to justify a Soviet invasion of, for the point, what Central Asian country with capital at Kabul?", "answer": "Islamic Republic of<b> Afghanistan</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "This man won his first election by appealing to a class he called \u201cMondeo Men\u201d and mocking his opponent\u2019s slogan, \u201cback to basics.\u201d This man, who was accused of crimes against humanity in the Chilcot Report, listed his top priority as \u201ceducation, education, education\u201d in a 1996 speech. The 7/7 bombings of the London Underground occurred during the leadership of, for the point, what Labour Prime Minister who was criticized for his role in the Iraq War and succeeded by Gordon Brown in 2007?", "answer": "Tony<b> Blair</b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "This tribe began a conflict when it intercepted a military column en route to Fort King, killing all but two of Francis Dade\u2019s group. Escaped slaves were welcomed in this tribe and subsequently called its \u201cblack\u201d members. This tribe fought the Battle of Negro Fort to resist relocation, but was forcibly moved in the Treaty of Payne\u2019s Landing. For the point, name this Native American tribe that was led by Osceola during the second of their three wars against the US in Florida.", "answer": "<b> Seminole</b>s", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "In this city, assisted housing was built following the 1953 Shek Kip Mei fire. A fort in this city had its walls torn down by Japanese troops to construct a runway for the nearby Kai Tak Airport. In this city, triads populated a once-walled city built in the Kowloon peninsula. This city features the I. M. Pei designed Bank of China Building in its Central district. Reclamation projects have reduced the size of Victoria Harbor in, for the point, what special administrative region that was given to China from Britain in 1997?", "answer": "<b> Hong Kong</b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {"question": "In this city, an image of 11 faces and red block letters reading \u201cWe Demand the Truth\u201d commemorates the Ballymurphy Massacre. A bombing in this city attempted to assassinate the leadership of the UDA on Shankill Road, but instead killed eight civilians. The Cupar Way peace line in this city was built to prevent rioting but has not been removed, despite the signing of the 1998 Good Friday Agreement in this city. Hundreds of political murals detailing \u201cthe Troubles\u201d are found in, for the point, what capital of Northern Ireland?", "answer": "<b> Belfast</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "When this figure was given a plot of land equal to the area covered by an oxhide, she cut the hide into small strips to encompass a nearby hill. This woman\u2019s first husband, alternately named Sychaeus or Acerbas, was a Phoenician priest in Tyre. This woman stabbed herself in front of her sister Anna and ordered a massive funeral pyre; that pyre is observed by a group of seafarers departing the African coast for Rome in an epic poem by Virgil. For the point, name this queen of Carthage who fell in love with Aeneas.", "answer": "<b> Dido</b>", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {}, {"question": "This leader claimed Ronald Richter had created nuclear fusion energy and that this man\u2019s country would sell energy in milk bottles. This man created the INPS, his country\u2019s first social security program, as Minister of Labour under Edelmiro Farrell. In 1973, left wing supporters of this ruler were massacred at the Ezeiza Airport, a year before this man\u2019s death and the beginning of the Dirty War. The descamisados, or \u201cshirtless ones,\u201d supported, for the point, what populist leader of Argentina who was once married to Evita?", "answer": "Juan Domingo<b> Per\u00b4on</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "In one speech, this man sought to render \u201cnuclear weapons impotent and obsolete.\u201d This politician urged the National Association of Evangelicals to \u201cbeware the temptation\u201d to ignore \u201cthe aggressive impulses of an evil empire.\u201d Although his staff denied that \u201cevil empire\u201d was a pop culture reference, weeks later, this man announced the Strategic Defense Initiative, which was nicknamed \u201cStar Wars\u201d by the press. For the point, name this politician who, when<em> The Empire Strikes Back</em> was released in 1980, was in the midst of his first successful Presidential campaign.", "answer": "Ronald<b> Reagan</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This scientist proved that diamonds are made out of carbon and wrote the seminal text<em> Elementary</em> <em>Treatise on Chemistry</em>. This scientist proved that nothing new is produced by combustion, a finding that completely disproved phlogiston theory. Due to his status as a nobleman, this scientist was accused of tax fraud and guillotined during the French Revolution. The law of the conservation of mass was discovered by, for the point, what father of modern chemistry?", "answer": "Antoine<b> Lavoisier</b>", "metadata": "Science - Chemistry"}, {}, {"question": "After this man was accused of masterminding a protest at the Qingming Festival, he was purged by the Gang of Four. This man, whose 1989 resignation allowed Jiang Zemin to seize power, established a Special Economic Zone at Shenzhen and paved the road for reacquiring Hong Kong with his \u201cone country, two systems\u201d principle. Market reforms were the chief goal of, for the point, what 1980s Chinese leader who crushed the Tiananmen Square protests?", "answer": "<b> Deng</b> Xiaoping ([dung], but be lenient)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "This author declared that \u201cWe have no gift to set a statesman right\u201d in his poem \u201cOn being asked for a War Poem.\u201d The final stanza of a poem by this author asks the questions \u201cWhat is it but nightfall?\u201dand \u201cWas it needless death after all?\u201d This writer imagined a man who knows that he will meet his fate\u201csomewhere among the clouds above\u201d in his poem about an airman who foresees his death. For the point, name this Irish poet of \u201cEaster, 1916.\u201d", "answer": "William Butler<b> Yeats</b>", "metadata": "Literature - British Literature - Poetry"}, {"question": "This party\u2019s economic policies were financed by MEFO bills, which allowed arms companies to take illegally large loans. This party published a 25-point platform, including immigration restrictions, the abolition of mercenaries, and the banning of war profiteering, that was never changed during its existence; that platform was developed by leaders like Anton Drexler and Dietrich Eckart. This party purged its paramilitary wing, the SA, during the Night of the Long Knives. For the point, name this fascist political party that ruled Germany under Adolf Hitler.", "answer": "<b> Nazi</b> Party (accept<b> National Socialist German Workers\u2019</b> Party or<b> NSDAP</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This thinker\u2019s clarifying remarks on freedom and emptiness are laid out in<em> The Ethics of Ambiguity</em>. Howard Parsley poorly translated this author\u2019s magnum opus in 1950. This author of the \u201cManifesto of the 343\u201d supporting abortion rights declared that even Mary Wollstonecraft defined men as the \u201cideal\u201d in a work that declared that \u201cone is not born, but becomes a woman.\u201d This wife of Jean-Paul Sartre was a major influence on Betty Friedan\u2019s<em> The Feminine Mystique</em>. For the point, name this French author of <em>The Second Sex</em>.", "answer": "Simone de<b> Beauvoir</b>", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {}, {"question": "A concerto that this composer wrote for Ferdinand IV of Naples was partially adopted for the second movement of a G minor symphony nicknamed for its use of \u201cTurkish\u201d instruments. This composer wrote a number of baryton trios for his longtime patron, as well as a symphony in F-sharp minor whose 3/8 [three-eight] coda features musicians blowing out candles and leaving until only two violins are left. The <em>Military</em> Symphony was written by, for the point, what composer who petitioned Prince Esterhazy for a vacation with his<em> Farewell</em> Symphony?", "answer": "(Franz) Joseph<b> Haydn</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "Philip II forced this monarch to sign the Treaty of Cateau-Cambresis, eight years after this monarch declared the \u201clast\u201d Italian War against Charles V. Diane de Poitiers was the long-time mistress of this king, who remained married to Catherine de Medici. This man sheltered a young Mary Stuart and married her to his son Francis in a bid to control Scotland. Gabriel Montgomery accidentally killed this monarch with a splintered lance. For the point, name this French king who died at a jousting tournament in 1559.", "answer": "<b> Henry II</b> of France", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "One holder of this position supported the Collier-Burns Act, earmarking funds for a freeway system. The EPIC [e-p-i-c] campaign was created by a socialist candidate for this position, Upton Sinclair. When Gray Davis held this position, he effectively ended the controversial Proposition 187, which banned illegal immigrants from using state services. Jerry Brown, the current holder of this position, succeeded the star of the<em> Terminator</em> movies, Arnold Schwarzenegger. For the point, name this political position based in Sacramento.", "answer": "<b> Governor of California</b> (prompt on partial answers) Page 11", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A child ruler of this territory, Hisham II, was exiled by Almanzor, whose rule as court official caused this territory to disintegrate into separate<em> taifas</em>. In 929, Abd al-Rahman III converted this territory from an emirate into a caliphate. This territory\u2019s namesake capital city was home to nearly one million people at its peak prior to its 1236 capture by Ferdinand of Castile during the Reconquista. For the point, name this territory of Islamic Spain, centered on an Andalusian city.", "answer": "<b> Cordoba</b> (accept Emirate of<b> Cordoba</b>, Caliphate of<b> Cordoba</b>, city of<b> Cordoba</b>, etc.; prompt on Spain and elaborations thereof before \u201cSpain\u201d is mentioned; prompt on Andalusia or al-Andalus before \u201cAndalusia\u201d is mentioned)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "The winning side in this battle was forced to rush to Austria\u2019s aid after a disastrous battle at Galicia. Hermann von Francois successfully encircled the Second Army in this battle, prompting its commander, Alexander Samsonov, to commit suicide. This battle\u2019s losing side was later mopped up at the Masurian Lakes, while the winning commander\u2019s fame would propel him to the presidency of Weimar [vye-mar]. For the point, name this 1914 victory for Hindenburg and Ludendorff over Russia, named in reference to a Teutonic loss five centuries earlier.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Tannenberg</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This figure popularized a loose fitting, white style of gown known as the chemise a la reine [she-meez ah lah ren]. She was painted in that garment, as well as in a red gown holding her three children, in works by her court painter Elisabeth Vigee-Lebrun. A sketch of this woman in profile with her hair cut short and wearing simple clothes was made by Jacques-Louis David [LOO-ee da-VEED] just before her execution by guillotine. For the point, name this Queen of France and wife of Louis XVI [16].", "answer": "<b> Marie Antoinette</b> (or<b> Maria Antonia</b> Josepha Johanna)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {}, {}, {"question": "This man allied with Lucius Saturninus to secure land for his troops. After a defeat at the Battle of Arausio, this man assumed command and won the Battle of Aquae Sextae. This man fought the Numidian king Jugurtha and defeated a Germanic invasion by the Cimbri and Teutones. Soldiers were nicknamed\u201c[this man\u2019s] mules\u201d for the large packs they had to carry on their backs, one of his reforms of the legions. For the point, name this Roman leader who served as consul seven times and was a rival of Sulla.", "answer": "Gaius<b> Marius</b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "This dynasty\u2019s founder abdicated after Li Shimin killed his brothers at Xuanwu Gate. Empress Wu Zetian\u2019s rule interrupted this dynasty, whose Emperor Zuanzong ordered the strangulation of Yang Guifei after blaming her for An Lushan\u2019s rebellion. The Abbasid Dynasty began making paper after defeating this dynasty at the Battle of the Talas River. The poets Li Po and Du Fu wrote during, for the point, what dynasty that ruled during the Golden Age of China in the 7th century AD?", "answer": "<b> Tang</b> Dynasty", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "Description acceptable. Helping these people was the goal of the domestic VISTA program. Martin Luther King was assassinated one month before the start of a planned campaign named after these people in 1968. The 1964 State of the Union Address laid out a series of programs to help these people, including the establishment of the Office of Economic Opportunity and the Head Start program. Lyndon Johnson\u2019s Great Society declared a war on the conditions of, for the point, what class of people who possess relatively little money?", "answer": "<b> poor</b> people (accept War on<b> Poverty</b>; accept equivalents related to people with<b> low income</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In this war\u2019s western theater, one side conquered the sites of Arish and Abu Ageila. During this war, William McGonagle was wounded by aircraft fire and more than two dozen sailors were killed in a torpedo attack against a research ship, the USS<em> Liberty</em>. One side in this war had announced that a closure of the Straits of Tiran would be considered an act of war; after that occurred, a preemptive air strike was carried out against the Egyptian air force. The Golan Heights, Gaza Strip, West Bank, and Sinai Peninsula were all captured by Israel in, for the point, what June 1967 war?", "answer": "<b> Six-Day</b> War (accept the<b> Third Arab-Israeli</b> War; accept the 19<b>67 Arab-Israeli</b> War before \u201c1967\u201d is mentioned; prompt on Arab-Israeli War; prompt on June War) Page 13", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "A story set in this city ends with Joe Hynes reading a poem to a group of people who enjoy a round of beer while gathering support for a politician on October 6th. In a story set in this city, Gretta relates how her one-time lover Michael Furey perished in a snowstorm after singing for her, causing Gretta\u2019s husband Gabriel Conroy to contemplate the nature of mortality. Charles Parnell is commemorated in \u201cIvy Day in the Committee Room,\u201d which is set in, for the point, what city that titles a collection of short stories, including \u201cThe Dead,\u201d written by James Joyce?", "answer": "<b> Dublin</b> (accept<b> Dublin</b>ers)", "metadata": "Literature - British Literature - Short Fiction"}, {"question": "Manuel Bonilla seized power in this country while backed by Sam Zemurray\u2019s Cuyamel Fruit Company. After accepting bribes to lower banana export taxes in the Bananagate scandal, Oswaldo Arellano was ousted as President of this country. For the point, name this country that was invaded by El Salvador in the Soccer War and which partially inspired the term \u201cbanana republic\u201d after the American military intervened in Tegucigalpa.", "answer": "<b> Honduras</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "One king of this name was targeted by the 1320 Shepherd\u2019s Crusade for his failure to participate in the Reconquista. Another king of this name was unable to defeat a Flemish uprising at the Battle of the Golden Spurs. A king of this name defeated King John at the Battle of Bouvines; that second king of this name was nicknamed Augustus and fought in the Third Crusade. The Knights Templar were destroyed by the fourth, \u201cfair,\u201d king of, for the point, what name shared by six kings of France?", "answer": "<b> Philip</b> (accept<b> Philip</b> the Tall or<b> Philip</b> V; accept<b> Philip</b> the Fair or<b> Philip</b> IV after\u201cFlemish\u201d is read; accept<b> Philip</b> Augustus or<b> Philip</b> II after \u201cJohn\u201d is read)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "James Randall wrote a song during this war that refers to the \u201cOld Line\u2019s bugle, fife, and drum.\u201dResidents of St. Helena Island sang \u201cMichael Row the Boat Ashore\u201d during this war. During this war, Julia Ward Howe wrote a new set of lyrics for a song whose title figure \u201clies a\u2019mouldering in the grave,\u201d\u201cJohn Brown\u2019s Body.\u201d For the point, name this war in which \u201cMaryland, my Maryland\u201d and \u201cThe Battle Hymn of the Republic\u201d were sung by Confederate and Union soldiers, respectively.", "answer": "American<b> Civil</b> War", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Misc Literature"}, {"question": "This mountain was first described to Western audiences after the book \u201cthe Capital of the Tycoon\u201dwas written by Rutherford Alcock, the first foreigner to scale it. After the Golden Gate Bridge, the world\u2019s second most prevalent site for suicides is located at the foot of this mountain in the Aokigahara forest. This mountain, Haku, and Tate, form the \u201cthree holy mountains,\u201d or<em> sanreizan</em>. For the point, name this active stratovolcano located in Honshu, the highest point in Japan.", "answer": "Mount<b> Fuji</b> (or<b> Fuji</b>yama) Page 14", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "This organization expelled its president, Ron Carey, in 1997 after federal investigators discovered he had taken hundreds of thousands of dollars in kickback donations for his 1996 re-election campaign. This group purged itself of corruption after its Mafia-connected first President, Cornelius Shea, was convicted of attempted murder. The AFL-CIO expelled this union in 1957 after it elected a man who, in 1975, disappeared outside the Red Fox Restaurant in Detroit. For the point, name this labor union once led by Jimmy Hoffa.", "answer": "International Brotherhood of<b> Teamsters</b> (accept<b> IBT</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A series of these objects in red, yellow, and blue with stenciled labels were painted in oil by a man more famous for depictions of American flags, Jasper Johns. The Ditchley portrait of Queen Elizabeth I shows her standing on one of these objects. Amerigo Vespucci, a creator of these objects, was honored by Martin Waldseemuller as the namesake of two landmasses on another of these documents. Cartographers create, for the point, what graphic depictions of borders and geographic features?", "answer": "<b> map</b>s (accept<b> map</b> of America until \u201cDitchley\u201d is read; accept<b> map</b> of the world throughout)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "George Labram designed a \u201clong\u201d gun named for this man that was used during the Siege of Kimberley. The satirical magazine Punch described his \u201ccolossus\u201d with one foot in Egypt and the other in South Africa. This man\u2019s hope that the US might rejoin the British Empire inspired a project giving people from Germany and current or former British territories two years of foreign study. For the point, name this British mining tycoon, the namesake of several prestigious scholarships and the former namesake of Zimbabwe.", "answer": "Cecil (John)<b> Rhodes</b> (prompt on \u201cLong Cecil\u201d gun)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}